<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-11-17T09:58:08-05:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Meng Xu</title><subtitle>Meng Xu&apos;s Personal Website</subtitle><entry><title type="html">I Passed Comps! Reflections, Struggles, and Tips for Future Students</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2025/i_passed_comps_reflections_struggles_and_tips_for_future_students/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="I Passed Comps! Reflections, Struggles, and Tips for Future Students"/><published>2025-07-21T19:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-07-21T19:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2025/i_passed_comps_reflections_struggles_and_tips_for_future_students</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2025/i_passed_comps_reflections_struggles_and_tips_for_future_students/"><![CDATA[<p>After weeks (okay, months) of mental marathons and self-doubt, I’m happy to say: I passed my comprehensive exams! As a non-native English speaker, this journey wasn’t just academic; it was personal. I want to share my honest experiences, emotional ups and downs, and some lessons that I hope will help future students walking (or stumbling) down this path.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Standing on the Shoulders of Those Before You</p> <p>First, talk to your advisors. Second, and equally important, reach out to senior students, even those who have already graduated. They’re your best resource. They’ve been through it, survived, and often carry wisdom no handbook captures.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Organizing Notes</p> <p>I started by reviewing and reorganizing my reading notes from classes. But remember, comps are not limited to what you learned in seminars. Just reviewing class readings isn’t enough. You’ll be amazed by how much you already know when you start preparing. Knowledge doesn’t only come from lectures; it also comes from projects and random conversations.</p> <p>This is how I organized my notes. I identified major theories and topics and organized my notes around them. What is this theory about? What are its assumptions, seminal works, antecedents, outcomes, limitations, and future directions? I also prepared several versatile research ideas that integrated multiple theories and topics, and I’m a big fan of them. If you’re asked to design a study for one theory, these pre-prepared ideas become your personal cheat sheet, so you don’t have to pull a rabbit out of a hat when the pressure is on.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Crafting Answering Strategy</p> <p>We were given a month to study. In the first two weeks, I focused on reviewing materials, and in the second half, I shifted to crafting my own answering strategy. As someone who studies strategy, having a strategy for comps felt…necessary?</p> <p>I practiced structuring my answers to be logical and clear. I used simple numbering (“first,” “second,” “lastly”) to guide the reader through my thoughts. Honestly, my brain felt like a tangled yarn ball with all the information I’d stored. But structuring my answers was like finding the beginning of the string: once I pulled it, everything flowed smoothly, and I could lay out my ideas in an organized way.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Who’s My Audience</p> <p>I often wondered: should I write at a basic level? But faculty already know this stuff. I imagined explaining to first-year students who had strong logic but little familiarity with the literature. For example, when discussing agency theory’s risk preferences, I didn’t just write “different risk preferences.” I added: Principals are risk neutral because they can diversify away firm-specific risks, while agents are risk averse because their wealth is relatively concentrated in one firm. Adding one sentence showed I understood the “why,” not just the definition. This is just my take, and I encourage you to talk to your advisor about what level of depth and explanation is expected in your program.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">The Practice Simulations</p> <p>I did a full 3-day simulation of the written exam. It helped me understand pacing, fatigue, and the emotional rollercoaster I’d face. But it was exhausting. I wasn’t in my best shape to continue studying for a few days afterward. My recommendation is that consider doing a simulation if you can, and time it wisely, not too far away from the exam as you are not “ready” yet and not too close to the exam as you may exhaust yourself. You don’t need to burn out before the actual exam. Allow time to recover.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Time Management</p> <p>The first thing I did each day when the exam started was to map out my time on scratch paper. I wrote down exactly what time I would start and finish each question. This helped me stay disciplined and avoid spending too long on any single part. I allocated time to each question, and when time was up, I moved on, no matter how tempted I was to keep writing. My goal was to answer every question. Sometimes, I had three points I wanted to cover but only enough time for one paragraph. In those moments, I made sure to address the most important point first. If I had time later, I could come back to add more (though honestly… that never really happened). Structuring my answers, as I mentioned earlier, also helped me stay focused and avoid rambling under pressure.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Emotional Management</p> <p>The comps also tested how I handle uncertainty and pressure. In the last two weeks before the exam, my brain felt like it was operating on fumes. Sometimes I blanked out and often wondered if I’d make it through this. Turns out… I did. If you feel like you’re losing steam before the exam, you’re not alone. Trust that knowledge (if you’ve mastered it) will come back to you when you need it, especially with the prompts in the exam.</p> <p>Also be kind to yourself. I think that it’s important to let go of the need to study perfectly every single day (yes, I’m looking at you, high achievers). Otherwise, you risk draining your emotional energy very soon.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Additional Tips for Non-Native Speakers</p> <p>There were times I felt like I had to work extra hard to express my ideas clearly and write at an academic level, but over time, I learned that clarity matters more than fancy words.</p> <p>I didn’t need to say:</p> <blockquote style="font-size: 1rem;"> “From the standpoint of perceptual phenomenology, the chromatic presentation of the sky emerges as a function of light dispersion processes…” </blockquote> <p>When all I truly needed to convey was:</p> <blockquote style="font-size: 1rem;"> “The sky is blue.” </blockquote> <p style="font-weight: bold;">The Oral Exam</p> <p>Before my oral, I was jittery, and I thought I had forgotten everything again. But when the questions came, I was able to think and respond. Our faculty members were supportive and warm, and as the conversation flowed, my stress level decreased. It felt like the type of conversation I’d have at a conference over coffee. Stay calm. Easier said than done, right? Yet, this seemingly simple advice holds immense power. It’s truly beneficial to pause and collect your thoughts before diving into an answer. It’s not about giving the perfect answer; it’s about showing how you think.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Final Thoughts</p> <p>Comps taught me that I’m more resilient than I thought. It’s easy to believe that fear, doubt, and fatigue are signs of weakness or impending failure, but I learned they’re not. Instead, they are universal human experiences that simply underscore the intensity of the journey you’re undertaking.</p> <p>At the end of the oral exam, I asked the faculty for feedback as I wanted to be able to share my experience with future students to help them navigate this daunting process. One faculty asked: “When do comps start? And what would you tell future students? I responded, “The day we start the program.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu Passed Comps]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Corporate Governance in the Sun: My ICGS Adventure at ASU</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/corporate_governance_in_the_sun_my_icgs_adventure_at_asu/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Corporate Governance in the Sun: My ICGS Adventure at ASU"/><published>2024-11-29T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-11-29T20:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/corporate_governance_in_the_sun_my_icgs_adventure_at_asu</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/corporate_governance_in_the_sun_my_icgs_adventure_at_asu/"><![CDATA[<p>This fall, I transformed into a conference-going whirlwind! It started with the AOM in Chicago in August, swept through the SMS in Istanbul in October, and landed at the ICGS in Tempe, Arizona, in November. While AOM and SMS might be household names for scholars, ICGS probably rings fewer bells—so let me tell you about this gem of a conference.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">What is ICGS?</p> <p><a href="https://icgsociety.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The International Corporate Governance Society (ICGS)</a> is a nonprofit organization aimed to promote research, teaching, and consulting on corporate governance. This year’s annual conference took place at Arizona State University in sunny Tempe, Arizona. Thanks to a generous doctoral travel grant from the Harold S. Geneen Charitable Trust, I had the opportunity to attend.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Conference Highlights: From Keynotes to Connections</p> <p>I arrived in Tempe Thursday night to participate at the PDW on Friday, and the main conference ran from Saturday to Sunday. It kicked off with a keynote on corporate purpose by Dr. Cannella and Dr. Finkelstein, two prominent scholars whose research I often cite in my own work. Day two brought another stellar keynote, this time by Dr. Ertimur, who dove into shareholder voting. As someone researching both corporate purpose and shareholder voting, I couldn’t believe how perfectly these talks aligned with my interest and work—it was like the universe was winking at me. My own presentation was scheduled on Saturday afternoon. Was I nervous? Oh, absolutely. But the thoughtful feedback and questions I received made it all worthwhile.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">What Sets ICGS Apart?</p> <p>Several areas made the ICGS a unique conference experience.</p> <ol> <li> <p>Corporate Governance Focus: The focus on corporate governance means every session felt like it was tailor-made for my interests, and everything was directly relevant and enriching.</p> </li> <li> <p>Interdisciplinary Spark: While corporate governance was the theme, the perspectives were far from monolithic. For example, a finance scholar presenting on CEO dismissal and performance cited a completely different body of literature than I do. It gave me fresh ideas to approach my work.</p> </li> <li> <p>Global Perspectives: True to its “International” name, the conference featured discussions across US, European, and Asian contexts. I learned how Japanese boards operate and how shareholder voting systems differ in Europe and the US.</p> </li> <li> <p>Theory Meets Practice: Industry practitioners shared real-world examples, including two experts who design executive compensation. Hearing their challenges reminded me how academic research can and should address practical issues.</p> </li> <li> <p>Intimate Vibes: Unlike the mega-conferences where I barely scratch the surface of connections, ICGS’s smaller size fostered meaningful conversations at the sessions and breaks. I reconnected with familiar faces and met others whose work I admire but had never met in person.</p> </li> </ol> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Beyond the Conference: Exploring ASU and Tempe</p> <p>Outside of the conference, I had a little bit of time to explore the campus of Arizona State University. Walking through campus and visiting the dining halls are my go-to ways to experience campus culture. During my three-day stay, I dined at Pitchforks and Hassayampa—pretty good, though I have to say UGA’s dining halls still reign supreme! I also enjoyed running through the flat campus (you know what I mean if you’ve visited hilly UGA). On my way back to the hotel from the historic Old Main, I encountered ASU students celebrating their football victory over UCF. The Sun Devils are doing pretty well this year (currently ranked 16th). This was my first-time visiting Arizona. The desert climate, the striking vegetation, and the beautiful ASU campus made for a memorable first trip. And note to future me: pack extra lotion. My Georgia skin was not prepared for the desert dryness.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Wrapping It Up</p> <p>The ICGS conference was an inspiring, motivating experience that exceeded all expectations. It reminded me of why I love research and why corporate governance matters. I’m deeply grateful to the Harold S. Geneen Charitable Trust for making my participation possible.</p> <p>I look forward to going back to ASU for another visit! But next time, I’ll come armed with hydration—inside and out!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Conference"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's ICGS adventure at ASU]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My First Year as a PhD Student</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/my_first_year_as_a_phd_student/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Year as a PhD Student"/><published>2024-06-02T18:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-06-02T18:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/my_first_year_as_a_phd_student</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/my_first_year_as_a_phd_student/"><![CDATA[<p>Hey everyone! Remember me? Your friendly neighborhood PhD applicant cheerleader who hasn’t posted anything in nearly a year? It turns out that PhD life can be a bit all-consuming. Well, guess what? I’m officially a one-year PhD student veteran!</p> <p>When I was told by several applicants that my blog inspired them during their challenging PhD application journey, it hit me: OMG there are people actually reading my ramblings! Feeling a sense of responsibility, I figured I’d pay it forward and share my first-year experience to help others on a similar path.</p> <p>Disclaimer: everything I’m sharing here is based on my own adventure and may not be applicable to yours.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Coursework: Reading, Writing, and Research Methods My BFFs</p> <p>I had six content seminars (3 OB, 2 Strategy, and 1 Entrepreneurship) and three methods classes in my first year. I am a self-proclaimed OB scholar because I have taken more OB classes than Strategy classes. Reading was intense. There were about 7 papers per course per week. Writing was not easy, either. We did multiple introductions, proposal, sometimes review, and of course presentations. The research methods classes were like a twisted mental gym – challenging but strangely satisfying.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Projects: Finding My Research Groove</p> <p>I find our classes very helpful, but the real learning comes from working on projects.</p> <p>Which project should I work on? We can either be invited to join projects or propose our own and convince faculty members to hop on board. I only experienced the first route so far. When invited, I try to get the details: project status, who else is involved, and most importantly, how I can contribute.</p> <p>How many projects should I be on? I think it’s a personal choice, but genuine interest is the golden rule. Research projects can run for several years, and we won’t be able to sustain it if we are not curious and passionate.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Mentoring: The Georgia Difference</p> <p>One thing that seriously impressed me is our mentoring. We don’t select our advisors right away; instead, we are paired with a coach who helps us navigate the first year. But the support doesn’t stop there! It feels like every faculty member becomes a mentor in some way. I appreciate a junior faculty member who takes the time to suggest relevant events for me to participate in and help me plan my career. I also appreciate a senior faculty member who is always available for students. I stop by his office with the intention to schedule a meeting, but he always invites me in for a conversation right away – that’s the kind of accessibility you find at Georgia.</p> <p>At the end of our first year, we choose our advisors. I think that at the end of the first year is a good timing. I have figured out my research interests and the work styles of faculty members. I believe that selecting an advisor deserves an in-depth exploration (maybe another blog).</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Dark Side</p> <p>Let’s be honest, it’s easy to let health and self-care fall by the wayside. For me, that meant gaining some weight and neglecting exercise. Thankfully, summer break provides a much-needed reset, and I’m more physically active and slowly getting back on track. Another hurdle I faced was the learning curve. Stepping back into academia after working in the industry for many years means I’m rusty. I am not as sharp as I was ten years ago. Being a non-native English speaker definitely adds another layer to the challenge. It’s naturally more difficult to read, write, and present. If you’re rocking a PhD in your non-native language, major high five!</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">A Final Takeaway</p> <p>I’m super grateful that I’m doing my study at Georgia. Sure, the football team is amazing (Go Dawgs!), but the faculty are the real stars. They’re supportive, knowledgeable (seriously, top in the field), and incredibly generous with their time. When I compare my experience to the horror stories on the PhD subreddit, I feel like I landed in a PhD paradise. So, what’s the takeaway for aspiring PhD students? Culture, culture, culture! I encourage you to talk to current students and faculty members to get a feel for their culture before application and experience the culture yourself during campus visit. For those of you who haven’t clocked in some industry time, you might not fully grasp the importance of workplace culture. In the industry, there’s a saying: “people don’t leave jobs, they leave toxic work cultures”.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's first year as a PhD student]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on My UGA Management PhD Application</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/reflections_on_my_uga_management_phd_application/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on My UGA Management PhD Application"/><published>2023-05-14T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-14T14:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/reflections_on_my_uga_management_phd_application</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/reflections_on_my_uga_management_phd_application/"><![CDATA[<p>Back in December 2022 when I was working on my application, I told myself that if I was admitted, I would write a blog to share my PhD application experience. So here I am.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">First, Answer the Question: Why Do You Want to Do a PhD?</p> <p>It took me quite a few years to make the decision to do a PhD. I have worked in the industry for seven years with a very decent job and promising career path, meaning the opportunity cost for me is significant. My goal is sharp and clear: I want to be a professor at a research university. Doing research – identifying a problem and solving the problem – gives me a strong sense of self-fulfillment. I get bored easily and I want to explore new topics continuously. In academia, I’ll be able to work with the smartest people who also share the same values as I do. It’s very important to understand what I am getting myself into. Some people quit halfway through because the academic experience differs from their expectations.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Choose the Right Programs to Apply to</p> <p>When I was evaluating which programs to apply to, I focused on:</p> <ol> <li>Research interest match. What are the faculty members’ areas of expertise? Do my interests align with theirs? I need to have an advisor who is a prominent scholar and who can provide guidance on how to do research in this field.</li> <li>Faculty research productivity. In the field of Management, we have <a href="https://www.tamugarankings.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TAMUGA Rankings</a>, which aggregate publications in the eight top-tier journals in Management by Management faculty in the U.S. business schools. It’s a great resource to understand the research productivity of each management program.</li> <li>Student placement. Placement is an indicator of the quality of the program as the objective of doing a PhD is to be placed at good research universities. It’s a great signal that a program can continuously place students as tenure track assistant professors at R1 universities.</li> </ol> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Plan Ahead and Start Early</p> <p>I wish I could have started early. Taking standardized exams, connecting with professors to get recommendation letters, doing research on the programs, drafting statements of purpose… All of these tasks take a considerable amount of time if you want to do them well. I love to visualize projects, and a roadmap was one of my favorite tools when I was working in the industry as a product manager. I created an application roadmap and mapped out project tasks, milestones and deliverables on a timeline to provide a high-level visual representation of the entire application process, so I knew where I stood and whether I was on track to completion or not.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">My Application Timeline</p> <p>I submitted my application at the end of December. I was informed that I passed the initial screening and was invited to an online interview around mid January. I did an one hour online interview with three faculty members at the end of January. A week after the online interview, I was invited to an on-campus visit at the end of February. I met with all the Strategy faculty members and current PhD students on campus. It was quite an intense visit. Three days after the campus visit, I received the offer in email.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Reflect: What I Did Well and What I Could Have Done Better</p> <p>I believe that having a strong motivation and understanding the academic expectations were crucial for me to get admitted. A couple of things that I could have done better include starting early as I didn’t start until the end of the year when I was a month away from the deadline and worrying less about standard test score as it is just a component of my application profile.</p> <p>I still feel very excited when I look back at my entire application journey, and I hope you find something useful from my reflections on my PhD application. Aspiring applicants, good luck and see you in academia soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's reflections of UGA management PhD application]]></summary></entry></feed>