<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2024-07-17T20:35:26-04:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Meng Xu</title><subtitle>Meng Xu&apos;s Personal Website</subtitle><entry><title type="html">My First Year as a PhD Student</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/my_first_year_as_a_phd_student/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Year as a PhD Student"/><published>2024-06-02T18:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2024-06-02T18:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/my_first_year_as_a_phd_student</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2024/my_first_year_as_a_phd_student/"><![CDATA[<p>Hey everyone! Remember me? Your friendly neighborhood PhD applicant cheerleader who hasn’t posted anything in nearly a year? It turns out that PhD life can be a bit all-consuming. Well, guess what? I’m officially a one-year PhD student veteran!</p> <p>When I was told by several applicants that my blog inspired them during their challenging PhD application journey, it hit me: OMG there are people actually reading my ramblings! Feeling a sense of responsibility, I figured I’d pay it forward and share my first-year experience to help others on a similar path.</p> <p>Disclaimer: everything I’m sharing here is based on my own adventure and may not be applicable to yours.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Coursework: Reading, Writing, and Research Methods My BFFs</p> <p>I had six content seminars (3 OB, 2 Strategy, and 1 Entrepreneurship) and three methods classes in my first year. I am a self-proclaimed OB scholar because I have taken more OB classes than Strategy classes. Reading was intense. There were about 7 papers per course per week. Writing was not easy, either. We did multiple introductions, proposal, sometimes review, and of course presentations. The research methods classes were like a twisted mental gym – challenging but strangely satisfying.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Projects: Finding My Research Groove</p> <p>I find our classes very helpful, but the real learning comes from working on projects.</p> <p>Which project should I work on? We can either be invited to join projects or propose our own and convince faculty members to hop on board. I only experienced the first route so far. When invited, I try to get the details: project status, who else is involved, and most importantly, how I can contribute.</p> <p>How many projects should I be on? I think it’s a personal choice, but genuine interest is the golden rule. Research projects can run for several years, and we won’t be able to sustain it if we are not curious and passionate.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Mentoring: The Georgia Difference</p> <p>One thing that seriously impressed me is our mentoring. We don’t select our advisors right away; instead, we are paired with a coach who helps us navigate the first year. But the support doesn’t stop there! It feels like every faculty member becomes a mentor in some way. I appreciate a junior faculty member who takes the time to suggest relevant events for me to participate in and help me plan my career. I also appreciate a senior faculty member who is always available for students. I stop by his office with the intention to schedule a meeting, but he always invites me in for a conversation right away – that’s the kind of accessibility you find at Georgia.</p> <p>At the end of our first year, we choose our advisors. I think that at the end of the first year is a good timing. I have figured out my research interests and the work styles of faculty members. I believe that selecting an advisor deserves an in-depth exploration (maybe another blog).</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Dark Side</p> <p>Let’s be honest, it’s easy to let health and self-care fall by the wayside. For me, that meant gaining some weight and neglecting exercise. Thankfully, summer break provides a much-needed reset, and I’m more physically active and slowly getting back on track. Another hurdle I faced was the learning curve. Stepping back into academia after working in the industry for many years means I’m rusty. I am not as sharp as I was ten years ago. Being a non-native English speaker definitely adds another layer to the challenge. It’s naturally more difficult to read, write, and present. If you’re rocking a PhD in your non-native language, major high five!</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">A Final Takeaway</p> <p>I’m super grateful that I’m doing my study at Georgia. Sure, the football team is amazing (Go Dawgs!), but the faculty are the real stars. They’re supportive, knowledgeable (seriously, top in the field), and incredibly generous with their time. When I compare my experience to the horror stories on the PhD subreddit, I feel like I landed in a PhD paradise. So, what’s the takeaway for aspiring PhD students? Culture, culture, culture! I encourage you to talk to current students and faculty members to get a feel for their culture before application and experience the culture yourself during campus visit. For those of you who haven’t clocked in some industry time, you might not fully grasp the importance of workplace culture. In the industry, there’s a saying: “people don’t leave jobs, they leave toxic work cultures”.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's first year as a PhD student]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on My UGA Management PhD Application</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/reflections_on_my_uga_management_phd_application/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on My UGA Management PhD Application"/><published>2023-05-14T14:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-14T14:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/reflections_on_my_uga_management_phd_application</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/reflections_on_my_uga_management_phd_application/"><![CDATA[<p>Back in December 2022 when I was working on my application, I told myself that if I was admitted, I would write a blog to share my PhD application experience. So here I am.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">First, Answer the Question: Why Do You Want to Do a PhD?</p> <p>It took me quite a few years to make the decision to do a PhD. I have worked in the industry for seven years with a very decent job and promising career path, meaning the opportunity cost for me is significant. My goal is sharp and clear: I want to be a professor at a research university. Doing research – identifying a problem and solving the problem – gives me a strong sense of self-fulfillment. I get bored easily and I want to explore new topics continuously. In academia, I’ll be able to work with the smartest people who also share the same values as I do. It’s very important to understand what I am getting myself into. Some people quit halfway through because the academic experience differs from their expectations.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Choose the Right Programs to Apply to</p> <p>When I was evaluating which programs to apply to, I focused on:</p> <ol> <li>Research interest match. What are the faculty members’ areas of expertise? Do my interests align with theirs? I need to have an advisor who is a prominent scholar and who can provide guidance on how to do research in this field.</li> <li>Faculty research productivity. In the field of Management, we have <a href="https://www.tamugarankings.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">TAMUGA Rankings</a>, which aggregate publications in the eight top-tier journals in Management by Management faculty in the U.S. business schools. It’s a great resource to understand the research productivity of each management program.</li> <li>Student placement. Placement is an indicator of the quality of the program as the objective of doing a PhD is to be placed at good research universities. It’s a great signal that a program can continuously place students as tenure track assistant professors at R1 universities.</li> </ol> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Plan Ahead and Start Early</p> <p>I wish I could have started early. Taking standardized exams, connecting with professors to get recommendation letters, doing research on the programs, drafting statements of purpose… All of these tasks take a considerable amount of time if you want to do them well. I love to visualize projects, and a roadmap was one of my favorite tools when I was working in the industry as a product manager. I created an application roadmap and mapped out project tasks, milestones and deliverables on a timeline to provide a high-level visual representation of the entire application process, so I knew where I stood and whether I was on track to completion or not.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">My Application Timeline</p> <p>I submitted my application at the end of December. I was informed that I passed the initial screening and was invited to an online interview around mid January. I did an one hour online interview with three faculty members at the end of January. A week after the online interview, I was invited to an on-campus visit at the end of February. I met with all the Strategy faculty members and current PhD students on campus. It was quite an intense visit. Three days after the campus visit, I received the offer in email.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Reflect: What I Did Well and What I Could Have Done Better</p> <p>I believe that having a strong motivation and understanding the academic expectations were crucial for me to get admitted. A couple of things that I could have done better include starting early as I didn’t start until the end of the year when I was a month away from the deadline and worrying less about standard test score as it is just a component of my application profile.</p> <p>I still feel very excited when I look back at my entire application journey, and I hope you find something useful from my reflections on my PhD application. Aspiring applicants, good luck and see you in academia soon!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's reflections of UGA management PhD application]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Access Paywalled Research Papers For Free</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/how_to_access_paywalled_research_papers_for_free/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Access Paywalled Research Papers For Free"/><published>2023-01-25T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-01-25T12:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/how_to_access_paywalled_research_papers_for_free</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2023/how_to_access_paywalled_research_papers_for_free/"><![CDATA[<p>First of all, I’d encourage you to check with your organizations. Organizations such as universities usually subscribe to journals relevant to their research. However, if you are not associated with any organizations but are interested in research papers, please keep reading this article.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Take Advantage of “Open Access” or “Free Access” Papers</p> <p>Some journals provide a few free articles in each issue. For example, Strategic Management Journal offers authors the ability to publish their articles Open Access: immediately free to read, download, and share. If a paper has the “Open Access” option, you can have access to the full text for free. This is how I had access to the first research paper that I’ve ever read.</p> <div style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 90%;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/open_access_research_paper-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/open_access_research_paper-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/open_access_research_paper-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/open_access_research_paper.png?22878eb0591220caad92c2b494bce2b1" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Open Access Research Paper" title="Open Access Research Paper" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Open Access Research Paper</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Become a Member of a Professional Association</p> <p>I will use the Academy of Management (AOM) as an example. Once you become a member, you will have access to AOM’s top-ranked and peer-reviewed journals, such as Academy of Management Journal and Academy of Management Review. Additionally, you will be able attend annual meetings and events to build your network and grow as a young scholar. What makes this membership even better is that the membership fee for a student is only $99 a year.</p> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Check Out the Author’s Academic Profile</p> <p>Some authors provide links to the full text of their research papers on their websites. It can be their faculty profiles created by the universities they work for, their personal websites, or their Google Scholar pages.</p> <div style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 65%;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/academic_profile-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/academic_profile-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/academic_profile-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/academic_profile.png?d46abb7213d4915f56c2a295dbdd2f9f" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Academic Profile" title="Academic Profile" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Academic Profile</figcaption> </figure> </div> <div style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; width: 100%;"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/posts/google_scholar-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/posts/google_scholar-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/posts/google_scholar-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/posts/google_scholar.png?03fa729a5d4db2ee9703403959eab1aa" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" alt="Google Scholar" title="Google Scholar" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Google Scholar</figcaption> </figure> </div> <p style="font-weight: bold;">Reach Out to the Author Directly</p> <p>You can also reach out to the authors, tell them that you are interested in their research, and ask if they can send you a copy of the paper. I know cold-emailing someone you don’t know can be a little bit awkward. The worst case scenario is that you don’t get a response, but if you do, this conversation could be a trigger of collaboration opportunity.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's solution of accessing paywalled research papers]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Tips for Beginners as a Beginner - How to Read a Paper</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2022/my_tips_for_beginners_as_a_beginner_how_to_read_a_paper/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Tips for Beginners as a Beginner - How to Read a Paper"/><published>2022-12-30T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-30T20:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2022/my_tips_for_beginners_as_a_beginner_how_to_read_a_paper</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2022/my_tips_for_beginners_as_a_beginner_how_to_read_a_paper/"><![CDATA[<p>A few years ago when I was doing my MBA at Georgia Tech, I attended a Lunch and Learn session for business PhD students because I was told that great food would be served. This was an annual event held at the business school for faculty and students to share their tips on how to do research and how to find a job in academia. Dr. Liu, a professor in Organizational Behavior, said he blocked half day every weekend to solely focus on reading the newly published papers in his field, and he had been doing it since he was a PhD student.</p> <p>Researchers spend a great deal of time reading research papers. I’m not even a PhD student yet, but after reading a few articles from the Strategic Management Journal, I’ve already discovered why every researcher should read a lot. I don’t plan to list all the reasons why reading papers is important. The purpose of this blog is to share my approach to reading a research paper as a beginner.</p> <p>I always start with the abstract, introduction, and headings. Sometimes I come across a topic that I’m not interested in or that I don’t have enough knowledge to understand. After reading the abstract and introduction, I’m usually able to decide whether I should continue or not. If the answer is yes, then I’ll go through the paper with greater care. Depending on the length of the paper, I usually spend more than one hour to grasp the details.</p> <p>Now comes my favorite tip! After reading a paper, I have an assignment for myself, which is to write a one-page review that summarizes the main points and my opinion of the paper. “My opinion” can be my opinion of the quality of the idea, impact of the research, limitations, etc. Having this assignment in mind makes reading more productive because I become more conscious of what I’m reading. When I first started to read research papers, I noticed an issue – my mind shifted away from reading quite easily. Mind-wandering in the case of reading has been characterized by task-unrelatedness, the absence of goal-directedness, stimulus-independence, unguided attention, and inward directedness (<a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.02648" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fabry and Kukkoonen, 2019</a>). Accordingly, the solution is to make paper reading goal-oriented, attention-guided, and stimulus-independent. I find that blocking time for reading, creating a distraction-free environment, setting a goal (the one-page summary assignment), and jotting down notes help me focus and organize my thoughts and prevent mind-wandering.</p> <p>I will keep updating this how-to blog once I become a PhD student and have more experience and tips to share. Stay tuned for “My Tips for Reading a Research Paper - Advice from a PhD Student”.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="PhD"/><category term="Research"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's tips of reading a paper]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why I Blog and Why You Should too</title><link href="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2022/why_i_blog_and_why_you_should_too/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why I Blog and Why You Should too"/><published>2022-12-10T20:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-12-10T20:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2022/why_i_blog_and_why_you_should_too</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://mengxu-readme.github.io/blog/2022/why_i_blog_and_why_you_should_too/"><![CDATA[<h4 id="never-forget-a-good-idea">Never forget a good idea</h4> <p>“Verba volant, scripta manent” is the motto I’ve chosen for my blog, and it’s also the one of the reasons why I blog. It is a Latin proverb which translates to “spoken words fly away, written words remain”. Periodically, I have innumerable thoughts running wildly inside my head. Sometimes a brilliant idea comes across my mind, but it’s highly possible that I’d forget about it if I decide to prioritize other work rather than jotting down the idea. I need to organize these thoughts and put them in a centralized place before they are pushed back to the back of my head, floating in the most remote realms of my mind.</p> <h4 id="turn-thoughts-into-work">Turn thoughts into work</h4> <p>For me, writing is thinking. Writing is a critical part of the creative process that sparks new ideas. When I write down something, even just a few bullet points, I’m more likely to keep refining the content, turning bullet points into paragraphs and eventually a presentable article. After all, the first blow is half the battle. This is especially important for researchers as we can’t wait to write until we have everything sorted out.</p> <h4 id="inspire-my-fellows">Inspire my fellows</h4> <p>A blog can be a perfect outlet to share my ideas that hopefully will inspire others. I plan to share my experience and my tips on, for example, how to read and write research papers, how to collect data, and how to present research findings, and hopefully my tips will motivate others who are pursuing a similar career path.</p> <h4 id="improve-writing-skills">Improve writing skills</h4> <p>What makes writing better? Writing more! Writing papers will always be looming in the background no matter which stage I am with my academic career. The more I write, the more familiar I am with my styles and the more aware I am with my weaknesses. Writing is like exercising, and I need to keep my writing muscles toned.</p> <h4 id="express-myself-freely">Express myself freely</h4> <p>A blog is a fantastic platform to express myself. Getting stuck while writing Statement of Purpose? Write a blog to spark some ideas. Feeling burned out during the qualifying exam? Write a blog to distract myself and give myself a break. Paper submission being rejected? Write a blog to vent and get my motivation back. Emotional and physical health benefits of expressive writing have been studied by <a href="https://www.apa.org/monitor/sep01/keepdiary" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a research published by the American Psychological Association</a>.</p> <p>This is my first time writing a blog, and I’m already loving it!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Meng Xu's reason of blogging]]></summary></entry></feed>